WWW.MY-SUBS.CO
Oh, let me give you one of those.
Can I give you one of those?
It's an open day at the Abbey.
Please come along, in aid
of the hospital trust.
- Hello, sir, might I offer you one of those?
- Thank you very much.
Please bring the family.
Would you like one of those?
But what are they paying to
see? We have nothing to show 'em.
A decent Reynolds, a couple
of Romneys and a Winterhalter.
That's your lot. They'd do better
- visiting the Tate.
- That's not the point.
People want to see a different sort
of home. It's not the things in it.
- How the other half lives?
- If you like. There's curiosity.
- Dr Clarkson, what do you feel?
- Keeping people healthy takes a lot
of money in this day and age. We
could raise more than you think.
Robert, we are opening
for one day for charity,
and there's an end to it. Mary
and Tom have made the decision.
Ah. I know well enough
that when Mary has spoken,
my opinion has little
bearing on the matter.
You don't really mind, do you?
No, but I think it's crackers.
I don't like it. Poking and
prying around the house.
What's to stop them slipping the odd
first edition into their back pockets?
You've a very poor opinion
of your fellow man.
I have the opinion that
life has taught me.
But I don't see why anyone would
pay good money to come and look.
- You're not curious about how
other people live. - No. I'm not.
And if you'd the chance to see the private
rooms of the King and Queen, would you pay?
But what would it tell me? They sleep
in a bed, they eat at a table. So do I.
I always wonder whether someone else
is having a better time than I am.
But that's what's so dangerous. You
think they must be having a better time.
Then you want them not
to have a better time.
- The next thing you know, there's a guillotine
in Trafalgar Square. - Ever the optimist (!)
I think all these houses
should be open to the public.
What gives them the
right to keep people out?
The law of property,
which is the cornerstone
of any civilisation worthy of the name.
Well, to me, it could be a good thing.
To let them enjoy fine craftsmanship
and beautiful paintings.
But then, of course, they're
bound to start asking,
"Why have the Crawleys got
all of this and I haven't?"
Thank you, Mr Molesley. I
couldn't have put it better myself.
But why have they, Mr Carson?
How is your job search going, Mr Barrow?
But why should anyone pay to
see a perfectly ordinary house?
Not everyone lives in a
house like Downton Abbey.
Oh, roll up, roll up, visit
an actual dining room!
Complete with a real
life table and chairs!
People have always tipped the
butler to look 'round a house.
Even Elizabeth Bennett wanted to
see what Pemberly was like inside.
A decision which caused her a
great deal of embarrassment,
if I remember the novel correctly.
And what about Robert?
He's still very ill.
He's on the mend. It's
been a few weeks now.
- And Cora's very competent.
- Mmm, yes, she's competent.
Leading a revolution
without turning a hair.
Anyway, it's agreed. Downton Abbey
will open to the public for one day.
Dr Clarkson is very grateful.
Clarkson was there? Oh,
so he really has weakened.
I prefer to think he
has begun to see sense.
You believe that? Even after Robert's life
was saved by a hospital being nearby?
You think that changes things,
but as Lord Merton pointed out,
Robert would have been treated
there even after the hand-over.
Oh? How is Lord Merton?
As he always is.
And you? You weakening?
No.
- No!
- Mmm.
Who was it?
Bertie Pelham. He's going to be in London
on the 11th, and he wanted to meet up.
Why don't you ask him to stop in here
on his way back to Northumberland?
- If you'd like to.
- I would rather.
- Is he worth it?
- As opposed to your car mechanic?
I'm a car mechanic, thank you.
We're opening the house that
weekend. He may have some ideas.
Well, I'll ask him.
I should go.
I'm late as it is. I'll be back tomorrow.
Don't feel you must look in every day.
You should be working for your exams.
- It can't be long now.
- Not too long, no.
Are you nervous? I should be.
I do know it. The question is, can
I summon it up when the time comes?
- Where are you taking them?
- The school.
The headmaster will oversee it. Mr
Molesley's settling the details.
- You owe him a great deal.
- I know. But he's enjoyed it, too.
Oh.
- This is for Mrs Patmore.
- What is it?
A note to thank her. I'm grateful.
- She already knows that.
- It never hurts to say it.
You don't want to encourage her.
She's too curious for her own good.
Just give her the note.
Oh. This is good of you.
You should've let one of
the footmen bring it up.
I wanted to see how you are, My Lord,
and... I thought you
might fancy some of this.
Crumbs. That looks frightening.
It's, uh, a little Chateau
Chasse-Spleen, My Lord.
I put it in this for ease of carriage.
Chasse Spleen? Now you're talking.
I believe it was a
favourite of Lord Byron's.
He knew a thing or two
about wine. And women.
But do you know, Carson, I think
I'm going to have to say no.
- Really, my Lord?
- I'm afraid so.
Sometimes in life
sacrifices have to be made,
and I think the time has
come for me to accept
that I cannot go on as I used to.
I am very sorry to hear
you say so, My Lord.
Not as sorry as I am.
And speaking of necessary sacrifices, I've
been thinking about things, lying here.
We must get on with
simplifying the household.
I know we've talked about it,
but we haven't really done much.
Oh, the new maids live in the
village, and so cost a lot less.
And we only have one
groom and a stable boy.
But we still have an under butler and
two footmen. In this day and age.
I do believe that Mr Barrow has genuinely
been looking for other employment.
But not finding it. Is there
anything we can do to help?
I'll speak to him, My Lord.
What do you think of the plan
to open the house for a day?
I think it's a dangerous
precedent, since you ask,
but I'm not sure how useful
it is of me to say so.
Dangerous? I think it's idiotic.
It adds up to the same thing, My Lord.
- It's a mistake. I suppose it's too
late to stop it now. - Far too late.
But what on earth can we show them to give them
their money's worth? Lady Grantham knitting?
Lady Mary in the bath?
What's this?
Oh, it's addressed to me.
Oh, it's from Mr Mason.
- How did it get there?
- I wondered where I'd put it.
- He asked me to give you it.
- Well, why didn't you, then?
I couldn't find it. It must have
fallen in the rubbish by mistake.
- Why had it been opened?
- Had it?
Whatever happened to that man?
Do you know what his sentence was?
- Ten years, m'lady.
- Ten years? My goodness.
I know. I'm glad in a way I didn't
have to testify against him now.
Good night, Baxter.
Are you here? What time is it?
It's late. Go back to sleep.
I think we ought to ask
Mama to come and see me.
- She must be feeling rather left out.
- Her mind is on other things.
She's hoping your operation will
persuade people over to her side.
I would have died if I'd
had to be taken to York.
But they'd still operate here in
an emergency, so nothing's changed.
Well, let's not make it worse.
I'm afraid it must get worse
before it gets better.
What about a fire?
It's a bit indulgent, but we've earned it.
- Not for me. I'm going to bed.
- You're not feeling ill, are you?
Anna, if you're not
well, you must tell me.
We've finished with this business
of your keeping me in the dark.
- I'm not ill exactly.
- Have you told Lady Mary?
- I didn't like to bother her. - Bother her
first thing. - I could tell Dr Clarkson.
No. You're seeing Dr Ryder
if you're seeing anybody.
Don't be silly. We can't afford that.
- I can't expect Lady Mary to keep shelling out.
- I'll pay. I have savings.
- We're selling a house, aren't we?
- Yes. To buy another house.
Now you're the one being
silly. Talk to her tomorrow.
She'll agree with me. And I'm paying.
I wouldn't mind having
breakfast here sometimes.
- Not every day, but sometimes.
- I don't think anyone would object.
How are you at making coffee?
I can make coffee. It's not very hard.
That's where you're wrong.
There's quite an art to it.
Uh, you might like to have
a word with Mrs Patmore.
Of course. If you'd like me to.
And I want to start bringing
things a little more up to standard.
I wonder if we could have the
hall boy to do some polishing.
I don't see why not.
And you might ask one of the
maids about making the bed.
- Isn't that good enough, either?
- It's not bad. I didn't mean that.
But I do like those sharp corners.
Well. I'm glad it's not bad.
I wish you'd told me before.
- I'm sure it's nothing.
- What does Bates say?
He wants me to see Dr Ryder again.
He wants to pay, but it
seems an extravagance to me.
I'm happy to talk to Dr Clarkson.
No, let's go to London. I'm
sure Dr Clarkson could manage it,
- but I feel like a jaunt.
- And stay the night?
With Lady Rosamund. Pack
something for the evening.
Medium smart. I'll make
some telephone calls.
- I got your message. What's happened?
- I'll ring for some coffee.
You sound as if you should
ring for some smelling salts.
If you mean is it serious, it is.
- I received a letter this morning
from the Board of Governors. - Go on.
They are going to combine us with York.
- As we knew they must.
- Indeed. I am to remain in my post here.
- Good. - Mrs Crawley is
to stay on as our almoner.
- Very sensible.
- But they want to offer
- the role of president to you.
- Me? Why?
You made a good impression
when you went into York.
I don't understand. What about Mama?
Lady Grantham is to be, and I quote,
"Allowed to step down after so
many years of noble service."
Golly. They've sacked the Captain.
You can see their point. How could they have
someone in the management of the new system
who thinks the whole idea
is a horrible mistake?
- And you support this notion?
- Of course he does.
He put your name forward as replacement.
Lady Grantham is not as young as she was,
- and, as Mrs Crawley says, I'm
afraid she'd be almost willing the
new regime to fail. - Probably.
Besides, I want to involve the new president
in the logistics of running things.
And she would never have
agreed to take that on.
So, I'm to step into her
shoes and then be given
more responsibility than she had?
We both think you'd be marvellous.
And who's going to tell her?
They'll write, as soon
as they hear back from me.
I need to talk to Lord Grantham.
The thing is, we don't want someone
to come up with another name.
Don't we? It might be easier
all round if they did.
Good. I'll see you at 8:00.
Don't tell him it's me.
I want to be the surprise guest.
Oh, you'll think of something.
All right, bye.
So this is the urgent business
that takes m'lady to London town?
- It's not the only thing.
- But it is getting serious.
Dinner with Evelyn
Napier at the Criterion?
Doesn't sound very serious to me.
I used to go to the
Criterion with Michael.
Do you have to put a damper on
every restaurant in the capital?
As a matter of fact, I have
very happy memories of it.
Send him my best wishes. I
hope to see him again soon.
Oh, Evelyn? Yes, send him my love, too.
Evelyn or whoever else might be there.
Why don't you come with me?
It'll be fun. I dare you.
- You haven't been anywhere in ages.
- All right. I'll go and pack.
We can't be too long. I want to be
sure we're ready for the opening.
Oh, we've masses of time for
that. We'll be home tomorrow.
Edith, you can manage for a
day without us, can't you?
I can manage without you
for as long as you want.
- Why don't you come with us? - And watch
Mary flirt with her oily driver? No, thank you.
- Can't you be pleased for her?
- I'm as pleased for her as she would be for me.
Barrow, you mustn't let him wear you out.
Oh, he's all right, m'lady. Aren't you?
- I was cheering him up.
- That's not what it looked like.
Do you need cheering up, Barrow?
We all need it sometimes, m'lady.
I mean it, George. You must let
Mr Barrow get on with his work.
Again, again...
All right. And off we go!
We're off. I'm taking Tom.
It's time he had a break.
Oh, I envy you. I'm so sick
of this room, I could scream.
Barrow was in the gallery, looking
rather glum. Do we know why?
We've talked about making
changes in the household.
Carson and I both feel
he's the obvious candidate.
You're not going to sack him?
I hope not. I hope he's
going to find another job.
Oh. I see. Well, that explains it.
He's awfully sweet with
George and the girls.
- You do know that? - And when
George is older, he can ask him back.
Goodbye, darling.
- Get some rest.
- Rest.
Don't worry, Bates.
We'll have her home soon.
I don't think there'll be anything
to concern ourselves about.
Anna has an appointment this evening.
I'll telephone you
after. Mr Mead won't mind.
I'm very grateful to you,
m'lady, for arranging it,
but Anna will ask him to send me the bill.
Dr Ryder was my idea, not yours.
And it was a good idea, m'lady.
An idea that has brought us
to within shouting distance
of our greatest happiness.
But I can pay my way, and I'd
be more comfortable to do so.
Very well. We won't fight about it.
- Will you miss me? - I miss you when
you're out of sight, never mind London.
I'm glad to hear it, Mr Bates.
I won't let them send him the bill.
That's not kind. His pride is more
important to him than the money.
Thank you, Mr Branson.
Mr Barrow, in 20 years' time,
I doubt there's one footman
working at Downton.
Lady Edith already manages without her
own maid, and if Anna were to leave,
I doubt that Lady Mary would replace her.
- It's not just you.
- But I am the first.
But you are the under butler,
a post that is fragrant with
memories of a lost world.
No-one is sorrier to say it than I am,
- but you are not a creature of today.
- And you are?
I don't believe that a house like
Downton could be run without a butler.
In that sense, yes, I am.
- Oh, you're busy.
- No, no. We're finished, Mrs Hughes.
Or at least one of us is.
Good day, Mr Carson.
I thought we might have our
dinner at the cottage tonight.
- If you like. - Perhaps you could
get some guidance from Mrs Patmore?
It doesn't have to be
anything very complicated.
Doesn't it? That's a relief.
I'll give you the date
as soon as I have it.
Right. I'm quite excited. How mad is that?
Can Mrs Patmore spare Daisy for the day?
For it will be the whole
day. There are six papers.
Oh, they'll spare her. Everyone
there thinks she's taking the right
step. Especially Her Ladyship.
I hope they appreciate your role
in all this. You've been very kind.
Well, I think it's because I
missed the boat that I feel
it's so important for others to catch it.
Mr Molesley, I've had an idea.
- What would you say to
helping me out? - What?
I'm not necessarily
suggesting you might teach.
I need a clearer idea of what you know.
But I like your respect for education.
I like your enthusiasm, and I
want to harness it if I can.
Oh, I don't know what to say.
First you can decide if you'd
sit a test of my own devising,
of general knowledge as much as anything.
This is kind of you, Mama, but
as you can see, I'm miles better.
I assumed it was a good sign that
I hadn't been summoned in haste.
Anyway, I'm here and I'm glad
of the chance to talk about
this mad scheme of opening the house.
It's all fixed, Mama. By Mary.
Well, why anyone would come
beats me, but, since it is,
should I cut a ribbon when
the doors are flung open?
Uh, well...
As president of the hospital,
I ought to have a formal role.
That is why we are raising funds.
I don't believe we need a ceremony.
The doors will be open from 9:00.
Who'd want to get here for then?
- Well, it wouldn't kill me.
- No, but it might kill us.
Oh, well, let me know what you decide.
The patients are my priority.
As president, I am their
representative on earth.
I have a feeling your
collapse will have changed
a lot of people's minds
about the so-called reforms.
Don't worry. I shall be
magnanimous in victory.
Is everything ready for tonight?
I think so. You're not
expecting a banquet, are you?
I'm expecting a delicious dinner
prepared by the fair hands
of my beautiful wife.
There's a threat in there somewhere.
I don't understand. He wants you
to sit the exam as well as Daisy?
Oh, no. Not matric. He wants
to assess my general knowledge.
- With a view to...
- He wasn't very specific.
I'd guess he didn't want to make
a promise he might have to break.
Are you going to take the test?
If Mr Carson gives me the time
off. What have I got to lose?
We'll meet upstairs after our
dinner. My room or yours?
- I don't mind.
- Mine, then. The lighting's better.
You're back. I thought I was
going to have to dress myself.
I am so sorry, m'lady. Only,
I could not get a bus.
Never mind. What did he say?
It's fine. Standard pregnancy pain.
Something to do with the ligament,
- but don't ask me what.
- I won't.
He gave me exercises and suggested
a warm towel if it lingers,
but it's just the body adjusting.
I don't think ligaments were invented
when I was having Master George.
Master George does make me laugh.
He rules Mr Barrow with a rod of iron.
Yes, Barrow's rather
sweet with the children.
Do you think he's trying
to get in with us?
I'd say he's genuine, m'lady. I
doubt he'll have any children of
his own, and he enjoys their company.
Miss Marigold's fitted
in surprisingly well.
- Yes, but then they're all...
- They're all what?
They're all clever and pleasant.
What were you going to say?
Just what I did say, m'lady.
Now, has Mr Talbot found
out you're coming tonight?
No. I suppose I should
have jumped out of a cake.
But then you'd have to wait for
the pudding before you saw him.
I must give Clarkson an answer, or
Mama will find out some other way,
before the letter arrives.
This is a secret, Baxter.
- Of course. Will that be all?
- Yes, thank you.
That was high risk.
Not really. She won't talk.
- Anyway, it'll be public soon.
- I suppose you want to accept?
I do. But not if it will upset you.
Mama's the one who'll be
upset when she's deposed.
Although the fact you're the
usurper who's stolen her throne
- will clearly make it worse.
- But if that wasn't an element?
I only worry if it's too much for you.
It sounds as if Clarkson
almost wants you to work there.
So?
I've had one career already,
bringing up my daughters.
They don't need me now,
so I'm ready for the next.
The girls still need you. But
anyway, isn't it time for a rest?
- You're not like Isobel.
- In what way?
I only mean you don't need a job.
I don't think she needs a
job. I think she wants a job.
She enjoys it, so would I.
- I'm not old, Robert.
- I didn't say you were.
Didn't you?
If Anna says she doesn't know
anything, I'm sure she doesn't.
Why must there be something to know?
If I find out you knew and didn't
tell me, I'd be terribly upset.
- I'd see it as a real betrayal.
- Don't say that.
So you are in on it.
- Welcome. - Evelyn!
- My hand is complete.
Darling.
Heavens. We are quite a party.
You know Lady Anne Acland,
Mrs Dupper and Mrs McVeigh?
Anne and I shared a governess,
and Jill and I came out together.
Small world. You know Henry Talbot, and I
think you met Charlie Rogers up at Brancaster.
- We've met again since then.
- This is Mary's brother-in-law, Tom Branson.
- Hello.
- You're over here.
I shall read lots into your wanting
to be a surprise. Am I right?
A table of singletons
at our age, well done.
Single now, we're all war widows.
I am not a war widow. Good
to see you again, Mr Rogers.
You, too. Although I haven't
been allowed to forget you.
Henry talks of nothing and nobody else.
Oh, I didn't think he knew
enough about me for that.
- Tell me, are you pleased with your
progress this season? - I certainly am.
- We're both driving at Brooklands next month.
- In the car you tested in Yorkshire?
Exactly. See? We'll get
you interested yet.
- No, you won't.
- Well, you've got me interested.
- Would you want to come?
- I don't get down to London much.
Well, you're here tonight. Why not come
specially? Watch from the pits with the team.
- Yes, I think you'd enjoy it.
- I know I'd enjoy it. Mary?
- Tom, you should go if you like.
- And what about you?
Well, I don't keep my diary in
my head. Ask me nearer the time.
How are we doing?
Ah, what is it?
Um, Glenvere smoked salmon, from
last night's upstairs dinner.
- Lemon?
- Oh.
- I don't believe it.
- What?
Mrs Patmore gave me two lemons, and
I left them on the kitchen table.
I'll tell you what would be
nice with this. Some horseradish,
thinned with a little soured cream.
I agree. That would be heavenly.
Except that we don't have any.
- Ah.
- What are we drinking with it?
The thing is, I don't
think we should drink.
Not if His Lordship feels
obliged to give it up.
But His Lordship is suffering
from a burst ulcer. We're not.
I know, I know. But
somehow it feels disloyal.
He is my officer, and I
should follow his lead.
- And it won't make you grumpy?
- I don't think so.
What's next?
- Duck.
- Oh.
Is the skin crispy like Mrs Patmore
does it? Did you ask her advice?
We certainly talked about what
it's like to cook dinner for you.
- Ah, I bet she had a lot to say.
- We both did.
- Good night. Shall I get us a taxi?
- Well, it's such a lovely night.
Why don't I walk you back?
Where are you based?
We're staying with my
aunt in Belgrave Square.
- Perfect. What do you say?
- I think it'd be nice.
Except I have a lot of reading to do,
so I might just go straight back.
- Only if you're sure, Tom.
- I'm sure.
- He'd better be sure.
- Well, I hope we meet again.
Perhaps at Brooklands. You'd have a good
time. It's really quite swanky these days.
How enchanting you make it sound.
Goodbye, Evelyn.
- You're a darling.
- Shall we?
I hope you will come south next month.
Partly to watch me driving of course,
but mainly so that I can see you.
- And I know you're not interested in racing.
- It's not only that.
I don't know why I haven't
told you before now,
but...
Matthew died in a car crash.
Yes, I know. Evelyn told me.
- So you understand.
- Of course I understand.
The car is your enemy. But it's my friend,
and all I ask is that you
give it a second chance.
After all, it's not as if you're
driving around in a Hansom cab.
Excellent. Um, in here.
Heavens, Mr Talbot. Is this
part of your plan to convince me?
Look. You don't have
to if you don't want to.
- Plenty of drivers' wives never
go near the race track. - Wives?
I only meant that if we do get involved,
it doesn't have to be part of the plan.
It's not compulsory.
But you'd like me there to watch?
Yes, but only so I can be near you.
Henry, to be honest,
this is moving much
faster than I'd imagined.
Look, I know I'm not what you're after.
My prospects are modest
at best, and you...
Well, you're a great catch.
But you're also a woman that I
happen to be falling in love with.
Gosh, that sounds rather
feeble, doesn't it?
No, not at all. As an argument,
I think it's rather compelling.
- Thank you.
- Mmm.
It doesn't show any signs of stopping.
- No.
- Should we run for it?
Well, you're the boss.
Come on. Careful.
- Were you caught in the rain?
- Not too badly.
We dashed for cover till
it slackened off a bit.
- How romantic.
- Why are you playing Cupid?
He's nice, he's mad about you and
he loves cars. I rest my case.
I don't see how it would work.
Why? He'll have to settle down eventually, go
into business. Why couldn't he do it from Downton?
- I know...
- He won't be as rich as you.
He won't be as rich as your child.
But he's a gentleman. And if
I say that, it must be true.
- Would you like a drink?
- Just a tiny glass of whisky and water.
- When does Edith's beau arrive?
- Friday.
- Just in time to interfere with the opening.
- I liked him when we met.
- He seemed a decent sort.
- But boring to an Olympic degree.
If Edith's happy, it
improves things for everyone.
She's so stupid to have
saddled herself with a child.
I mean, Marigold's sweet, but why
would any man want to take her on?
I thought you'd forgotten me.
Thank God I've found you.
The car wouldn't start, so I
had to get Stark to do it.
I'm glad I don't have to walk
the whole length of the drive.
- Hop in.
- I will. But first...
That feels so nice and automatic.
- Which is good?
- It is for me.
I hope you don't mind my taking a chance,
but I got your letter and
I wanted to discuss it.
This is Miss Cruikshank.
She's engaged to Larry.
- Yes. I saw it in the papers.
- I know I've rather pushed in,
- but I did so want to meet you.
- Does your fiance know you're here?
I gather you and he haven't exactly
seen eye to eye in the past.
Not exactly, no.
As you can imagine, I was amazed
and very pleased when she asked
if she could join me to pay a call.
You mustn't blame him.
It was completely my idea.
Mmm. Well, life is full of surprises.
- I know you and Larry rather got off on the
wrong foot. - That's one way of describing it.
Well, please know not all of Lord
Merton's family feel the same way.
Goodness.
After that, I don't know if I
can concentrate on business.
I wondered if old Lady Grantham
had received the letter.
Not that I've heard of. Although Dr Clarkson
has told them that Cora is happy to serve.
Uh, only we're coming to the house
opening on Saturday to support it.
Well, don't say anything if you see her.
I hate things like this. We'll all come
off very badly when she does find out.
- I'm afraid that's
probably true. - Mmm.
It's odd to think you'll be sitting
side by side, writing exams.
Well, my paper won't be
anything like as long as Daisy's.
- She's got six to do.
- Thanks.
I admire you, Daisy. To give
yourself a second chance.
When the time comes,
Daisy'll need some lunch.
- Maybe I will, as well.
- Well, I've thought of that.
I'll do lunch for Mr Dawes, too.
You could ask Mr Mason to join
you on the day. He'd enjoy that.
Don't bother him, not when
he's got so much work to do.
I'll tell him as soon as we have a
date. See if he'd like to look in.
I don't understand why you
can't just leave him alone.
- Daisy, that's not very gracious.
- Well, I don't!
It's nerves. She's worked
long enough for this moment.
It's partially nerves, yes.
But I don't think it's all nerves.
And I will write a note to Mr Mason.
This is nice. Now we can go down together.
- Less nervous making.
- Absolutely.
But I was going to look
into the night nursery first.
- Can I come?
- Of course.
Good evening, Nanny.
- This is Mr Pelham.
- Good evening, sir.
- Good evening.
- M'lady, could you be here
- while I just run down to
the sewing room? - Of course.
This is Mary's son, George,
and my late sister
Sybil's daughter, Sybbie.
And this is Marigold.
God bless you, Marigold.
What a lovely place this is to grow up.
I hope so.
I'm an experienced housemaid and a
housekeeper for how many years? And
he doesn't think I can make a bed.
Well, you always knew he was
old to be trained as a husband.
- Good evening.
- What are you doing here?
I thought I'd look in.
- What's that for? - I brought these
to say thank you to Mrs Patmore.
- You've already said thank you.
- That's very nice of you, Mr Mason.
Why bother? Have you seen
the kitchen gardens here?
There's enough vegetables to feed an
army. You need 'em more than we do.
Oh, never mind her, Mr Mason.
I think it's a lovely thing,
to have fresh farm vegetables just for me.
I'll make soup and stock and all sorts.
Well...
I'll leave you to it.
You've probably thought of
this, but I'd place someone,
maybe a servant, in each
room the public will enter.
- Just to keep an eye on things.
- Literally.
- I think that's a good idea.
- Carson, can you sort it out?
Of course, m'lady. I understand
it's only the ground floor.
And not too much of that. They'll
start in the small library,
then through the big library,
into the painted room,
the drawing room, the smoking
room, the great hall,
in and out of the dining
room and back outside.
Rope off across the
staircases and the back wing.
Who are the guides?
Do we need guides? Can't they just
have a look and leave it at that?
I don't think so. Not if you
want them to go away happy,
and leave behind what's not theirs.
Who knows about the history of the house?
Only our librarian, Mr
Pattinson, but he's away.
You'll have to fake it. Lady
Mary, Edith, Mr Branson...
Not me. I don't know a thing.
I'll sell tickets, but that's it.
Well, then, Lady Grantham, you and your
daughters can take parties of 10 each,
with no more than 30 in
the house at any one time.
- Crikey.
- Heavens.
I feel like the Belgians
waiting for the invasion.
Or the monkeys in a zoo.
- Do you all know your positions?
- Are we allowed to sit, Mr Carson?
Well, the place will
be open for nine hours.
Find an inconspicuous chair in the corner,
but keep a sharp eye out and stand
if any member of the family comes in.
What about the upstairs luncheon?
- Sandwiches in Her Ladyship's room.
- We'll set up two of the tea tables.
Mr Molesley can serve, and his place
in the hall will be taken by Daisy.
And look respectable.
Right.
Do you know where my walking stick is?
I thought I might equip
myself with it for tomorrow.
In case you catch a thief red-handed?
You never know. But
it's not at the cottage.
And I wonder if it might have
got left behind in my wardrobe.
- He knows a lot about everything.
- The trouble is, I think he does.
- Did you enjoy our London spree?
- I did.
Have you decided if you're coming
to Brooklands? I will if you will.
I know I won't enjoy it one
bit, but at the same time...
- You'd like to see him again.
- It's not that.
I could see him for a walk in the park.
No, I suppose I want to get
over it. To get over myself.
He asked me if I'd give cars
another chance. Perhaps I should.
Who is this flexible
and reasonable person?
I don't recognise my
own dear sister Mary.
- Could this be love?
- Oh, shut up.
He seems nice, and he's certainly
organised. Tom was quite jealous.
But what are his prospects? An
agent stuck up in Northumberland
managing someone else's estate?
What are Edith's prospects?
Oh, I don't know. With her magazine,
I think she could develop into
one of the interesting women of the day.
Ten years ago, that very idea
would have filled you with horror.
I've changed, you've
changed, the world's changed.
He is a gentleman. You can't
object to him on that score.
If she loves him, I don't
object to him on any score.
But I don't think we should encourage it.
She took him to meet Marigold,
but she didn't tell him why.
- Nor should she.
- She must eventually.
Let her make that decision for herself.
Now, you need some sleep before
your hideous day tomorrow.
Andrew? What were you
doing in Mr Barrow's room?
We were... I was borrowing a book.
What book? Where is it?
I left it there. I'll get it in the
morning. Good night, Mr Carson.
Oh, Andrew, Andrew, place
the table here, please.
Yes, Mr Carson.
Thank you, Mr Molesley.
I'm sorry for the wait, can
you form parties of 10?
We've been here since 9:00.
You are in the next group.
No, the third Earl built it.
Well, he didn't really build
it so much as envelope it,
because this room is originally medieval.
It was the monks' refectory of an abbey
that King Henry sold after the
Dissolution of the Monasteries.
Is that why it's called Downton Abbey?
I guess so.
Who painted that?
I'm not sure, but this...
This is a Reynolds, so
that is worth looking at.
And that's quite good, too.
Tell us about these people.
Oh, well, they were all rather marvellous
and sort of living that life.
- It's not very cosy, is it?
- Isn't it?
It is cosy at night, with
the lamps and the fire.
What about the architect?
Sir Charles Barry? Yes, he
built the Houses of Parliament,
or at least he finished them.
And, you know, he built
lots of lovely big buildings.
No, that's him, I think. Or his son.
Or it might be his father.
Who's the little girl?
Ah, the little girl is a little boy,
but who I could not say. Ah,
Granny, thank God you're here.
What else could I tell
them about the library?
The library was assembled by
the fourth Earl. He loved books.
- What else did he collect?
- Horses and women. Where's your mother?
- She's in the great hall.
- Thank you.
Excuse me please. Thank you.
Why are those shields on
the chimneypiece blank?
Do you know, I've never
really noticed that before.
Isn't that strange? I haven't
a clue is the answer.
Cora!
Excuse me.
Did you know when I was last here?
Mama, I think maybe we should...
And you let me babble on about
my victory? Have you told Robert?
- Mama, you of all people don't want
to bore our vis... - Just be quiet.
Excuse me. Hmm. Oh!
- Are you all right? - I was going
to see if Her Ladyship needs anything.
She needs a glass of water and a
fan, if you'd heard what I heard.
- What is it?
- I've had a letter. From Coyle.
- What? - He wants me
to visit him in prison.
Well, don't even answer it. Ignore
it completely. Throw it on the fire.
Mr Molesley, there's no-one
on duty in the library!
Right away, Mr Carson.
Uh...
Daisy, can you relieve me? I
ought to get the tables upstairs.
- What about the sandwiches? - I'll
take them up when I've got the
tables organised. - Oh, tablecloths!
Oh.
You wouldn't believe what happened
up there. In front of everyone.
Oh? Try me.
My son's wife, whom I have
treated like a daughter.
- Too like. - That she should
connive at my humiliation,
should revel as I am cast into the dust.
Steady the buffs. Cora doesn't
control this any more than you.
You've had different opinions,
but neither of you made it happen.
If only Mr Chamberlain had spoken...
He was never going to say
a word. The truth is, Mama,
officialdom doesn't care
what we think any more.
Our influence is finished.
You can say that! You, whose
very life has been saved.
You know dealing with
emergencies won't be affected.
- Do be logical.
- I am sick and tired of logic!
If I could choose between
principle and logic,
I'd take principle every time!
Just tell Cora I do not
wish to see her face
until I'm used to having
a traitor in the family!
Why is she in such a tizzy?
Well, you know mothers. They get
terribly wrought up about things.
- My mum does.
- There you are.
Mine does too.
May I ask what you're doing here?
I come to see your house.
With my mum and dad.
Do they know where you are?
- No. Why is it so big, your house?
- I'm not sure, really.
It's the way they used to manage things.
Well, why not buy somewhere comfy?
- You must have enough money.
- Maybe.
But you know how it is. You
like what you're used to.
Why are you in here?
- Wouldn't you like to know!
- Cheeky rascal!
Let him go. No harm done.
Are you sure, My Lord? Shouldn't
we shake out his pockets?
I don't think so.
He was more of a philosopher than a thief.
- So your house is finished?
- Finished and ready to receive my guests.
- And who'll run it day-to-day?
- My niece. My sister's girl.
She's agreed, so I'm all set.
Oh, and how will you attract the visitors?
Put an advertisement in the papers.
But how will they get in touch?
How do you think?
- I've installed a telephone in the house.
- Your own telephone?
My, my. You're blazing a trail now.
Have you found anyone
to hit with that yet?
If I had my way, I'd hit the lot of them.
- But it's going all right?
- Well, it seems so.
- Mr Carson, can I have a word?
- Certainly. - I'll leave you to it.
It's something or nothing.
Only, I'm a bit worried about Andy.
Now, it may be innocent. I'm
not saying I'm infallible.
But he's young, and you ought to know.
Lady Grantham, how nice.
Uh, this is my soon-to-be
daughter in law, Miss Cruikshank.
She was curious to see the Abbey, so I
bought her here to support the opening.
I've already taken her
to meet Mrs Crawley.
What did your fiance say to that?
Forgive me, but I think there's
been a misunderstanding.
- Larry isn't Mrs Crawley's enemy. - No?
He gives a marvellous impression of it.
Please tell Mrs Crawley when you
see her that I am her friend.
I would never want to stand in
her way. And nor will Larry.
I promise. Not while I'm around.
- Oh, yes, very interesting.
- Oh, interesting and encouraging.
Yes, I'll leave it at interesting for now.
Good day to you both.
Mama, can I speak to you?
No, you may not.
- Is dinner finished?
- It is.
They've had coffee taken up
to Her Ladyship's bedroom,
so they don't want us there.
What a day.
- I hope you've thrown away that letter.
- No, not yet.
I think you should.
- I don't know. I have to think.
- Think about what?
Nothing that would interest you.
You don't know what might interest me.
Well, that's rather what I
want to talk about, Mr Barrow.
Do you want us to leave
you to it, Mr Carson?
If you wouldn't mind.
I hope you're not planning
to hit me with that.
No. But I will not beat about
the bush either, Mr Barrow.
Someone has reported that you seem
to have a private
understanding with Andrew.
Not this again.
I might not have given it
much mind, but I was upstairs
last night quite late, and
I saw him leave your room.
Mr Carson, how long do I have
to work in this house before
- I am given any credit?
- That is all very well,
but we are talking about
a vulnerable young man,
- and I must look to his welfare.
- Yes. And if I were to give you
my word of honour that nothing took
place of which you would disapprove?
If I could just be sure.
So my word is still not good enough,
Mr Carson, after so many years?
I only wish it were.
Golly, Moses. You astound me.
- And all from the sale of tickets?
- It's a great deal of money.
I don't suppose we could open
the house on a regular basis?
- For charity, you mean?
- No, for us.
The house costs money to run, and
at the moment, it doesn't raise a
penny for washing its own face.
Tell me you're not being serious, Tom.
To charge money so people can come and snoop
around our home? What a revolting suggestion.
- It is rather a frightful idea.
- All right.
There may come a day when we
simply can't ignore such a large
source of income at our fingertips.
- Hopefully when I am dust.
- Still, Tom and Isobel were right.
People are curious about
what it's like to live here.
Which is sad in a way.
- Why? - Because it means our way
of life is something strange,
something to queue up
and buy a ticket to see,
a museum exhibit, a fat
lady in the circus.
Trust you to cast a pall of
doom over our successful day.
I had a visitor, a child
who'd escaped his mother.
He thought we were mad to live here
- when we could be so comfy in a normal house.
- Oh, I refuse to listen.
Downton Abbey is where
the Crawleys belong.
I hope we'll stay as long as we can.
- But I suppose we all realise it may not
last forever. - Oh, this is weakling talk.
George and I are made of sterner
stuff than the lot of you.
- That, I'm sure, is quite true.
- And we are not going anywhere.
Henry Talbot has invited us
all to Brooklands next week.
I think they'll have to drag you out,
as you break your fingernails
catching at the door case.
- English language never lets you down.
- Oh, shut up!
When I pass you I expect
to see you cheer and wave.
Come on, God bless you, come on!